Guide to the Kenneth J.Arrow Papers, 1939-2009
Kenneth J.Arrow Papers, 1939-2011
Arrow, Kenneth J., 1921-
71.8 Linear Feet ca. 43,250 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book Manuscript Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The Correspondence and Personal Files Series are RESTRICTED.
In addition, patrons must sign the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights form before using this collection.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Kenneth J.Arrow were donated to the Duke University David M. Rubenstein Rare Book Manuscript Library beginning in 1994.
Biographical Note
1921 Born in New York, NY
1940 B.S., Mathematics, City College of New York
1941 M.A., Mathematics, Columbia University
1942-1946 Weather Officer, US Army Air Corps (ret. Captain)
1947 Married Selma Schweitzer
1947-1949 Research Associate, Cowles Commission for Research in Economics
1948-1949 Assistant Professor of Economics, University of Chicago
1948- Consultant, the RAND Corporation
1949-1968 Acting Assistant Professor, Associate Professor, and Professor of Economics and Statistics, Stanford University
1951 Ph.D., Economics, Columbia University
1951 Publication: Social Choice and Individual Values
1954 Publication (with G. Debreu): Existence of Equilibrium for a Competitive Economy, Econometrica, vol. 22, pp. 265-290.
1957 Awarded John Bates Clark Medal by the American Economics Association (AEA)
1962-1963 Economist, President's Council of Economic Advisers
1968-1979 Professor of Economics, Harvard University
1972 Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences
1973 President, American Economics Association (AEA)
1980 to date Professor of Economics and Operations Research, Stanford University
1983-1986 President, International Economic Association (IEA)
Arrow has also been a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and a member of the National Academy of Sciences.
Collection Overview
The Kenneth J.Arrow papers, 1939-2009 (bulk 1980s-1995), document primarily the latter part of his career as an economist, professor, and Nobel Laureate. The collection provides a broad overview of his many professional activities; administrative activities for various associations and committees and for his universities; and political activism in research notes, draft papers and speeches, and correspondence. Arrow's career is especially distinguished by his contributions to the theory of social choice, including his book Social Choice and Individual Values, published in 1951, and his contributions to general equilibrium theory. For these achievements, Professor Arrow has been awarded the Johns Bates Clark Medal (1957) and the Nobel Memorial Prize in Economics (1972), which he shared with Professor Sir John Hicks. With an eleven year interruption at Harvard University from 1968 to 1979, Professor Arrow has spent the largest portion of his career at Stanford University. He has served as president of the American Economics Association and the International Economics Association, and has also been a member of the National Academy of Sciences. Some of the larger and more salient files in the collection include research notes on general equilibrium theory in economics; consulting on global climate change and contingent valuation; correspondence with Frank Hahn, Leonid Hurwicz, Alain Lewis, and Lionel McKenzie; and notes from graduate courses with Harold Hotelling. Although the collection contains primarily professional papers, there are some personal files as well as some concerning politics and activism.
The Conferences, Lectures, and Speeches Series includes information on organizations such as the Santa Fe Institute, National Bureau of Economic Research, Social Choice and Welfare Conference, American Economics Association, and International Economics Association. General equilibrium theory material is in scattered files not only in this series but also in the Notes, Papers, and Research Series.
In the Committees and Consulting Series are files on three extended projects on economic growth and policy, global climate change, and contingent valuation. Also, the American Economics Association, International Economics Association, and the National Academy of Sciences are represented. There is a subseries on economics journals.
The Correspondence and Personal Files Series includes correspondence with a number of eminent economists, including M. Allais, G. Debreu, M. Friedman, F. Hahn, J. Harsanyi, L. Hurwicz, T. Koopmans, L. McKenzie, R. Marschak, and R. Radner; with other scholars such as N. Chomskey, S.J. Gould, and J. Hirschleifer; with politicians, including D.P. Moynihan; as well as extensive notes and correspondence with some of Arrow's Ph.D. students, including A. Lewis.
In the Notes, Papers, and Research Series are notes on production functions, stability, uncertainty; economic theory, optimization, and decentralization; National Science Foundation grants; Social Choice and Multicriterion Decision-Making; and notes from courses with Harold Hotelling.
Departments of Economics are represented in the Stanford and Harvard Series, and the Miscellaneous Series has a folder on Arrow's Nobel Prize. The Politics and Activism Series contains files on the Middle East, arms control (especially Economists against the Arms Race), human rights, and UNESCO.
The remainder of the collection consists of unprocessed additions to the collection. Boxlists and summary descriptions of this material can be found in the detailed description below. Some of these additions have restrictions. Please consult the reference archivist before coming to the library to use these materials.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Harvard University. Dept. of Economics.
Stanford University. Dept. of Economics.
International Economics Association.
Social choice.
Economics--Sociological aspects.
Economics.
Contingent valuation.
Economists--United States.
Social action.
Equilibrium (Economics)
Climatic changes.
Hahn, Frank.
Hurwicz, Leonid.
Hotelling, Harold, 1895-
Lewis, Alain A.
McKenzie, Lionel W.
Contents of Collection
- Conferences, Lectures, and Speeches Series, 1971-1995 (bulk 1980s-1995).
  Documents many of Professor Arrow's public speaking engagements and activities at conferences, especially after 1980. These include regular conferences organized by the American Economics Association, the Econometrics Society, the International Economics Association, the National Bureau of Economic Research, the Sante Fe Institute, and other institutions, as well as other trips and engagements.
  - Invitations Declined (Box 1)
  - Abrahms Lectures
  - Actuaries Club
  - American Economics Association (AEA) Meeting, Dallas, 1984
  - AEA
    - Economics Theory Session, 1989
    - 1990
    - Meeting, Anaheim, 1993
    - Meeting, Boston, 1994 (Ely Lecture)
    - Meeting, Washington, DC, 1995
  - Arrow- Hurwicz Workshop, 1977 (Informational Issues in Decentralization)
  - Associated Students of Stanford University (ASSU) Conference, 1984
  - Barcelona Lecture, 1990 (Excellence and Equity in Education)
  - Basel Conference, 1987
  - Behavioral Foundations of Economic Theory, 1984-85 (Rationality of Self and Others)
  - Bellagio Conference, 1992
  - Camp Lecture, 1978
  - Camp Lectures, 1980 (Possibility of Economic Policy)
  - Centennial Symposia, 1990 (Information Explosion)
  - Center for Economic Policy Research, 1986-87 (Economics of Public Debt)
  - CERES Conference on Global Food and Technology Issues in the 21st Century, Williamsburg, 1990
  - Chinese Information Science, 1992 (Box 2)
  - China Trip Diary, 1979
  - Collegium Budapest, 1993
  - Complexity Workshop, 1986
  - Contingent Valuation Method Conference, 1984
  - Corporation Conference, 1987
  - Cowles Symposium, 1981-86 (Cowles in the History of Economic Thought)
  - Differential Information, Market Failure, and Public Policy, 1977
  - Disorder and Order, 1981
  - Eastern Europe Conference, 1989
  - Ecology and Economics, 1988
  - Econometrics Society Meeting, Barcelona, 1990
  - Econometrics Society Meeting, Korea, 1991
  - Economic Conflict Program, Office of Naval Research, 1976
  - Economics of Income Distribution, 1978
  - Economics of National Security, 1986-88
  - Edge Lecture
  - Elster Colloquium, 1985-86
  - Elster Central Bank Conference, 1992
  - Environmental Policy Decisions, 1990 (Environmental Policy As Political Conflict)
  - FACS Institute for Journalists, Asilomar, CA, 1989
  - Federazione delle Associazioni Scientifiche e Tecniche (FAST) Meeting, Milan, 1992
  - Florence, 1986
  - Florence Bioethical Conference, 1992
  - Ford Foundation, Future and the Welfare State, 1984
  - Friedman Panel, 1987
  - General Equilibrium Conference, 1993
  - German Business Congress, 1993-95
  - German Trip, 1990
  - Greater Talent Network, 1988
  - Grunberg Lecture, 1994 (Economic Transition Speed and Scope)
  - Hamburg Seminar, 1989
  - Hao Ran Foundation Workshop, 1989-90 (On the Socialist Economic Reform) (Incentive Problems in the Transition in Socialist Countries)
  - Harsanyi Conference, Berkeley, 1990-91 (Ethics in Business Contribution of John Harsanyi)
  - Health Economic Research Organization (HERO) Session, 1973
  - Hicks Conference, 1988-90 (Certainty Equivalence and Inequivalence for Prices)
  - Hong Kong Lecture, 1993
  - Hoover Anti-Trust Conference, 1984
  - Hoover Conference on Economic Transition, 1991
  - Hungarian Trip, 1983
  - International Economics Association (IEA)
    - Conference, 1984
    - Conference on Incomes Policy, Mexico, 1985
    - Congress Addresses
  - IEA (Box 3)
    - Congress Addresses
    - Congress VIII, India, 1986
  - IEA (Box 4)
    - Congress VIII, India, 1986
    - Forthcoming Conferences
    - Social Choice Session, 1989
    - Congress IX, Greece, 1989
    - Partnership Conference, 1990
    - Meade Conference, 1991
  - IEA (Box 5)
    - Congress X, Information Economics, Moscow, 1992
    - Congress X, Graduate Education, 1992
    - Income Inequality Conference, 1993
  - India Trip, 1986-87
  - Industrial Ecology, 1991
  - Innovation Diffusion, 1986
  - Iowa Lecture, 1992
  - International Environmental Policy Conference, 1993
  - Interpersonal Comparability Conference, 1986-88
  - International Society for Inventory Research, Economics of Inventory Management, Budapest, 1988
  - Jerusalem Summer Workshop, 1992
  - Jerusalem Summer Workshop, 1993
  - Karlsruhe Seminar, 1988-90
  - Keynesian Workshop, 1978 (The State of Keynesian Economics)
  - Keystone Center, 1990-91
  - Knoer Seminar, 1978 (Economies of Distributions)
  - Korea Development Institute, 1991
  - Kyung Hee University, 1984
  - Lazarfeld Lecture, Columbia University, 1993 (Methodological Individualism An Adequate Basis for the Social Sciences?)
  - Long Term Productivity Trends, 1989
  - Management Development Program, 1986
  - Manne General Equilibrium Workshop, 1984
  - Markets for Information, Ownership, and Control, 1988-89
  - Maxwell Lecture, McGill University, 1992
  - Mexico Lecture, 1990 (Transitions from Socialism)
  - Michigan/Sante Fe Instititute (SFI) Outpost, 1992
  - Miscellaneous Seminars, 1981-83
  - Moscow Trip, 1990
  - Mathematical Sciences Research Institute, 1985-86
  - National Academy of Sciences (NAS), Academy Forum, 1973-79
  - National Academy of Sciences (NAS), Industrial Ecology Conference, 1991
  - National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER)
    - Conference, 1971-72
    - Economic Fluctuations Meeting, 1987-88
  - NBER (Box 6)
    - Conference on Econometrics and Mathematical Economics, 1990-91
    - Economic Growth Conference, 1991
    - General Equilibrium Conference, 1992
  - Nemetria, Etica Ed Economia, 1993
  - Neuberger Conference on the Structure and Behavior of Economic Organizations, 1992
  - Nevada Kenney Talk, 1987
  - Nonlinear Analysis Congress, 1991
  - North Carolina Trip, 1988
  - Notre Dame Income Distribution Conference, 1992 (The Changing Distribution of Income in an Open US Economy)
  - Office of Naval Research Symposium, 1986
  - Olin Lecture, 1988 (The Economics of Law)
  - Operations Research Symposium, 1987
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) Conference, 1989
  - ORSA/TIMS, Epistemic Uncertainty in Rational Decision, San Francisco, 1992
  - Paris Trip, 1986
  - Pittsburgh Lecture, Philosophy of Science, 1990
  - Politico-Military Decision Making Workshop, 1985
  - Pomona Lecture, 1988 (Economics and Ethics of Income Distribution)
  - Poverty Seminar
  - Queens University Talk, 1974-78
  - Royal Economic Society Conference, London, 1991
  - St. Norbert Conference, 1990
  - Sabre Foundation, 1989
  - San Diego State Talk, 1990
  - San Francisco Mathematics Collaborative, 1986
  - Santa Clara Lecture, 1985
  - Santa Fe Institute
    - Evolutionary Paths of the Global Economy, 1987
    - The Economy as an Evolving, Complex System, 1988
    - The Economy as an Evolving, Complex System, 1989
    - Global Security Workshop, 1989
    - Growth and Cities Workshop, 1991
    - Workshop on Learning, 1991
    - Biology and Economics; Theoretical Computation in Economics, 1992
    - Complex Adaptive Systems Workshop, 1992
    - Increasing Returns Workshop, 1992
    - Organizational Adaption and Learning Workshop, 1993
  - Shell Lecture, 1983
  - Sienna Conference, 1991
  - Southern Economic Association Conference, 1981
  - Social Choice and Welfare Conference, Caen, 1991 (Political Conditions for Economic Reform in Eastern Europe)
  - Socialist Agriculture, Budapest, 1990
  - Southern Economic Association, 1981
  - Spoleto, Padua, 1987 (Information as a Service Industry)
  - Stanford Center on Conflict and Negotiation (SCCN), Conference on the Barriers to the Negotiated Resolution of Conflict, 1992-94
  - Stanford Center on Conflict and Negotiation (SCCN), Conference on the Barriers to the Negotiated Resolution of Conflict, 1992-94, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Stanford Institute of Theoretical Economics (SITE):
    - Workshop on Irreversibility, 1992
    - Workshop, 1993
    - Workshop on Economics of Inequality, 1993
    - Workshop, 1994
  - Strategic Economic Decisions Conference, 1992
  - Stonybrook Game Theory Seminar, 1992
  - Taiwan/ Hong Kong Trip, 1981
  - Tanner Lecture:
    - Oxford, 1983 (The Welfare-Relevant Boundaries of the Individual)
    - Harvard, 1985 (The Unknown Other)
    - Harvard (audio tapes), 1985
    - Stanford, 1986
  - Technion Guardians, 1992 (Israel's Economy in the Last Decade)
  - The Institute of Management Sciences (TIMS) Meeting, Rio de Janeiro, 1991
  - Theories of Economic Justice Seminar
  - Transfer Programs, 1978
  - Trinity University Lecture, 1984 (My Development as an Economist)
  - University of Calgary Speech, 1978 (Rational Discourse and Conflict in Values and Judgment)
  - University of California, Davis Lecture, 1979
  - Weizmann Institute Dinner, 1992
  - Western Economic Association Meetings, San Francisco, 1992
  - Western Economic Association Meetings, 1993
  - Western Michigan Talk, 1988-89 (The State of Economic Science)
  - Williams College Lecture, 1992
  - Williamson Organization Conference, 1991 (Scale Returns in Communication and Elite Control of Organizations)
  - Wingspread Conference, 1982 (Planning and Uncertainty)
  - Wisdom Toward the 21st Century Symposium, Osaka, 1983 (The International Economic Order of the 21st Century)
  - World Health Organization, Meeting on the Economics of Tropical Diseases, 1986
- Committees and Consulting Series, 1980s-1990s.
  Includes both administrative work for various committees and institutions, as well as work as a paid consultant on several projects. The latter includes three extended projects, one on economic growth and policy for the Canadian Institute for Advanced Research, one on climate change for the National Academy of Sciences and one on contingent valuation (the use of surveys to value public goods) for the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Association. The former includes work for the American Economics Association and International Economics Association, as well as for the City College of New York, the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development,; RAND, the Santa Fe Institute, and other organizations. It also includes a Journals Subseries with Arrow's work on various editorial boards.
  - Abt Associates (Box 7)
  - Abt Jobs
  - Aix-Marseille Center/GREQE
  - Alaska-National Energy Policy
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences Western Center
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences Western Center (Box 8)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science
  - American Association of University Professors
  - American Economics Association (AEA)
    - Committee on USSR Relations
    - Committee on Political Discrimination
    - Committee on Graduate Training
  - AEA/Social Sciences Research Council
    - China Exchange
    - South Africa n Students
    - Miscellaneous
  - American Foreign Policy Inc.
  - American Philosophical Society
  - American Society for Technion Israel Institute of Technology
  - American Statistical Association
  - Berkeley Mathematical Sciences Research Institute
  - Bioeconomics Society
  - Bishops
  - Pastoral Letter on Catholic Social Teaching
  - Bundeskanzler Fellowship
  - Canadian Institute for Advanced Research
  - Economic Growth and Policy
  - Center for Foundational Studies (Box 9)
  - Center for Operations Research and Econometrics (CORE)
  - Center for Risk Analysis
  - Center for Study in Israel
  - Centre d'Etudes Prospectives d'Economie Mathmatique Appliques a la Planification (CEPREMAP)
  - City College of New York
  - City College-Minorities Center
  - City College-Scholarship endowment
  - Charles River Associates
  - Committee for Economic Recovery
  - Delhi School of Economics
  - East-West Center
  - Econometrics Society
  - Econometrics Society-continued
  - Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC)
  - Einstein Archives
  - Electric Power Research Institute (EPRI)
  - Encyclopedia of Economics
  - The Esmee Fairbairn Research Center
  - European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD)
  - European University Institute
  - Fair Share
  - The Electric Rate Structure in Massachusetts
  - Federation of American Scientists
  - Fels Center of Government
  - Food Safety Council, Social and Economic Committee: Principles and Processes for Making Food Safety Decisions
  - Foundations and Applications of Utility, Risk, and Decision Theory (FUR)
  - Haldi Associates
  - Institute for Economic Theory
  - Institut d'Etudes Politques de Paris
  - Institute of Medicine, (2 folders)
  - Institute of Medicine Committee on Environment (Box 10:)
  - International Economics Association (IEA)
  - IEA-AEA
    - Booklet (The IEA: Past and Future)
    - Correspondence (Luc Fauvel,; Jean Paul Fitoussi,; Patricia Hillebrandt,; Michael Kaser,; Amartya Sen,; Paulo Sylos Labini,; Victor Urquidi)
  - IEA (Box 11)
    - Financial Advisory Committee - UNESCO
  - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis
  - International Society for Inventory Research
  - Irvine Advisory
  - Israel English Language College
  - Jerusalem, Institute for Ethics and Economics
  - Jet Propulsion Laboratory
  - Effectiveness of the Army
  - King's College
  - Maastricht Economic Research Institute on Innovation and Technology (MERIT)
  - MacArthur Foundation
  - National Academy of Sciences (NAS), (3 folders)
  - NAS (Box 12)
    - Budget and Internal Affairs - Government-University-Industry Roundtable
    - Human Rights Committee
    - Markets and Organizations
    - Minorities
    - Nuclear War Committee (Estes Award)
    - Population Statement
    - Status of Mathematics
  - National Research Council-Climatic Impact, (5 folders)
    - Cost-Benefit Analysis
    - Regulation
  - National Committee for Full Employment
  - National Science Foundation (NSF)
  - National Acid Precipitation Assessment Program (NAPAP)
  - National Acid Precipitation Assessment Program (NAPAP), (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - National Oceanic and Atmospheric Association (NOAA)
  - Notes and Drafts
  - New Palgrave
  - New Palgrave-Money and Finance
  - Northeast Asia Forum
  - Omicron Delta Epsilon
  - Paris Ph.D.
  - Poverty Institute
  - Pontifical Council for Justice and Peace
  - Price Institute
  - RAND-Discount Rate
  - RAND-Graduate School
  - Resources for the Future (RfF)-Role of Analysis in the Policy Process
  - Riverside Case
  - Santa Fe Institute
  - Economics Program, General
  - Santa Fe Institute, (20 folders) (Box 14)
  - Santa Fe Institute-Summer Program
  - Seidman Award Selection Committee
  - Sino-American Market Information Research Center at Stanford (SAMICS)
  - Sloan Behavioral Economics Program
  - Society for the Advancement of Social-Economics (SASE)
  - Stanford Center on Conflict and Negotiation
  - Stanford Institute of Theoretical Economics (SITE)
  - Tinbergen Institute/ International Journal of Development Planning Literature
  - USSR Institute of Control Sciences
  - Visitation Committee for Graduate Program, Review of Department of Economics at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst
  - Western Economic Association Nominating Committee
  - Wharton Risk and Decision Processes Center Advisory Committee
  - Wharton Risk and Decision Processes Center Advisory Committee (Box 15)
  - World Bank
  - World Institute for Development Economics Research (WIDER)
  - World Resources Institute
  - Yale Program on Non-Profit Organizations
  - Journals Subseries
    - American Economic Review
    - American Prospect
    - Bell Journal
    - Business in the Contemporary World
    - Complexity
    - Economics and Philosophy
    - Fundamentals of Economics
    - Group Decision and Negotiation Journal
    - Journal of Complexity
    - Journal of Corporate and Industrial History
    - Journal of Health Economics
    - Journal of Mathematical Economics
    - Journal of Official Statistics
    - Industrial and Corporate Change
    - Information Economics and Policy
    - Lux Mundi
    - Mathematics in Education
    - Mathematics of Operations Research
    - Organization Science
    - Philosophy and Public Affairs
    - Review of Economics and Statistics
    - Science
    - Society for Research in Economics
    - Stochastic Analysis and Applications
- Politics and Activism Series, 1974-1994.
  Contains files of Professor Arrow's personal political activities. These include especially work for peace in the Middle East, for arms control, in support of human rights and dissidents, and with other causes. These are collected in the Middle East, Arms Control, Human Rights and Miscellaneous Involvements Subseries, respectively. It also includes a UNESCO Subseries for his work for that organization.
  - Middle East Subseries (Box 15)
    - American Professors for Peace in the Middle East (APPME) ( Oil and the Arab-Israeli Power Balance by Arrow), 1977-90
    - Beyond War, 1987-91
    - International Center for Peace in the Middle East, 1988-91
    - Israel Democracy Institute (IDI), 1990-92
    - Israel-Diaspora Institute (IDI), 1990
    - Mid-East Center for Economic and Institutional Development, 1989-90
    - Middle East Policy (Includes correspondence with George McGovern), 1992
  - Arms Control Subseries
    - Center for International Security and Arms Control, 1985-90
    - Coalition for a Comprehensive Test Ban, 1993
    - Economics of Arms and Disarmament, 1989-91
    - Economics of Arms Reduction, 1991-93